Guide to the Estela and Ernesto Bravo Film and Video Collection TAM.616
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series XXV: Those Who Left, 1980-1981; 479242
  - "Escoria" of Union City Interviews, undated; cuid18533; 479662 (Box 58, Cassette ref1319, Box 98, Dvd ref1319)
    This video features black-and-white footage of interviews with Cuban men who left Cuba for the United States. The footage features a series of on-the-street interviews conducted by Estela Bravo in Union City, New Jersey in which she asks the men why they traveled to the United States and what they hoped to find. The majority of the men interviewed were living in the United States for less than a year at the time the interviews were conducted. Many mention that they left Cuba because they did not agree with the communist government. Others explain that they left to find better work and earn money although several mention that they have had a difficult time finding work in the United States. They likewise describe finding it difficult to get adequate housing and access to medical care. One man notes that he has received little support from the existing Cuban community in the US, and has received more support from other immigrant groups including Puerto Ricans and Dominicans. Some of the men mention travelling to the US as part of the Mariel Boatlift. The term "escoria" refers to a statement made by Fidel Castro about Cuban exiles, comparing those who left to escoria (scum).
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:57:25.
  - "Free Havana (Havana Libre) 2 Outside Immigration", circa 1980; cuid18484; 467255 (Box 37, Cassette ref798, Box 97, Dvd ref798)
    This video begins with an interview with a man who traveled from Miami to Cuba to visit family. In this segment he discusses his impression of the country, which he contrasts with his experience of traveling to Jamaica. The video then changes to on-the-street interviews with Cubans, many of whom express their interest in leaving the country for the United States or Canada. They discuss their reasons for wanting to leave, and what they hope to find outside of Cuba. Many express dissatisfaction with the government and a desire be reunited with family members who have already left Cuba.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:22:18.
  - "Free Havana (Havana Libre) 1 Common people's opinion", circa 1980; cuid18483; 467259 (Box 37, Cassette ref794, Box 97, Dvd ref794)
    This videos features several short on-the-street interviews and segments of footage filmed in Havana around 1991. The video begins with a brief interview with a taxi driver about his work and life in Cuba. The segment is followed by a 10-minute interview with a Cuban military leader and a Spaniard living in Cuba named Ignacio "el Gallego" Gonzalez. They talk about three Spaniards, including Gonzalez, who fought for Castro during the Cuban Revolution. The end of the video features on-the-street interviews with individuals in Havana about increased tourism in Cuba, and their opinions about people from the Cuban exile community traveling back to the country.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:22:04.
  - Footage: Carlos Muniz and interviews with Cuban Immigration staff, circa 1980; cuid18475; 467264 (Box 94, Cassette ref789, Box 83, Dvd ref789)
    Carlos Muniz Varela (1953-1979), along with his sister, was sent from Cuba to the United States in 1961 as a part of Operation Peter Pan. He later became an outspoken activist in favor of normalization between the United States and Cuba. On April 28, 1979, Muniz was ambushed while driving in San Juan, Puerto Rico and shot several times, most likely by individuals from a counterrevolutionary organization.
    The first eight minutes are old black and white footage telling the story of Carlos Muniz. There is no sound. This is followed by Estela Bravo interviewing a room of women in uniform. They are from the Cuban Immigration Department. The final few minutes appear to involve working men outside. There is a line of people waiting to obtain passports. All of the footage is in Spanish.
  - Footage including events and interviews, 1980; cuid18476; 468050 (Box 89, Cassette ref3, Box 75, Dvd ref3)
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:10:20.
  - Interview with Estela Bravo, circa 1980; TW_TAM_616_ER_14
  - "Mariel Flotilla (Those Who Left)", circa 1980; cuid18490; 467359 (Box 34, Cassette ref694)
  - Union City Interviews, 1980; cuid18534; 479618 (Box 55, Cassette ref1276)
  - Union City Interviews, circa 1980; cuid403; 479707 (Box 66, Cassette ref1360, Box 98, Dvd ref1360)
    This video contains on-the-street interviews with Cuban exiles in Union City, New Jersey. Footage on this tape is duplicated on tape ref1319. Video quality of this tape is poor.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 01:02:26.
  - "Union City #2, AL's Hub Caps, Ricky in Apt and Drugs #1", undated; cuid18535; 467360 (Box 34, Cassette ref693)
  - Those Who Left (Los Que Se Fueron), circa 1980; cuid399; 479611 (Box 55, Cassette ref1269, Box 96, Dvd ref1269)
    This is an almost complete full-length version of the documentary feature Those Who Left (Los Que Se Fueron). Video quality of this recording is poor in places and the recording ends abruptly before the credits appear.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 01:02:11.
  - Los Que Se Fueron 1st Part, circa 1980; cuid18478; 479624 (Box 55, Cassette ref1282)
  - "Los Que Se Fueron", circa 1980; cuid18480; 479646 (Box 57, Cassette ref1303)
  - "Los que se Fueron", circa 1980; cuid18489; 467579 (Box 24, Cassette ref474)
  - "Los Que Se Fueron Prob Tracking", circa 1980; cuid18491; 479623 (Box 55, Cassette ref1281)
  - "Those Who Left #1", circa 1980; cuid18477; 479244 (Box 45, Cassette ref980)
  - Those Who Left: Second Part, circa 1980; cuid18479; 479245 (Box 45, Cassette ref981, Box 97, Dvd ref981)
    This video contains a portion of the documentary Those Who Left. Video quality of this recording is poor and does not include a complete copy of the documentary.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:19:52.
  - "Those Who Left", circa 1980; cuid18481; 479619 (Box 55, Cassette ref1277)
  - "Those Who Left Historical Footage with Sound #2", circa 1980; cuid18482; 479674 (Box 58, Cassette ref1331)
- Series XXVI: The Three Rafters, 1992; 479605
  The 1992 documentary The Three Rafters(Tres Balseros) tells the story of two brothers and their cousin who left Cuba illegally on a raft to Miami. They did not tell anyone about their journey, and after a few months of living in the United States, they asked to Cuba's representatives in the United States for permission to return. They were finally able to return to Cuba, and upon their arrival, they share their experiences with relatives who knew nothing of their travels to the United States. Footage from this documentary includes scenes from the three rafters' arrival in Cuba and possibly a full-length copy of the film.
  - Tres Balseros, 1992; cuid400; 467378 (Box 31, Cassette ref675, Box 95, Dvd ref675)
    This video contains footage of three Cuban men returning to Cuba and greeting friends at family at an airport. The footage does not contain any audio, but features footage of the men speaking to the camera, and meeting with family after their arrival in Cuba.
  - Three Rafters: Arrival at Airport, 1992; cuid18492; 479736 (Box 60, Cassette ref1389, Box 98, Dvd ref1389)
    This video features footage of the three rafters arriving in Cuba. The footage shows them traveling through customs and then greeting their families. It features brief interviews with the men and their families. One man's mother says she is happy to have her son home because she was afraid he would never return. The men discuss their desire to return to Cuba once they were in the United States and what they hope to do with their futures after they have settled back into life in Cuba.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:22:58.
  - "Balseros de Jaime R; more campaign stuff", 1992; cuid18493; 479607 (Box 54, Cassette ref1265)
  - "Cojimar, Jaime R, Jose Marti Airport", 1992; cuid18494; 479608 (Box 54, Cassette ref1266)
- Series XXVII: Who Am I: The Found Children of Argentina, 2005-2014; 479628
  The 2007 documentary Who Am I? provides a continuation of Estela Bravo's 1985 film, Missing Children, tracing the struggle of families of those disappeared during Argentina's "Dirty War" (1976-1983) to discover the fate of their loved ones and to recover the kidnapped children of those who were killed. This film centers on an organization of women known as the " Grandmothers of the Plaza de Mayo" who gained worldwide recognition for their weekly demonstrations in the center of Buenos Aires and their continued search for missing children.
  The film includes interviews with the found children and with people who knew their parents, as well as trial footage related to the prosecution of individuals responsible for carrying out state-sponsored violence against political dissidents. Records in this series include a completed copy of the documentary, raw footage, and a press and promotional materials related to the release of the film.
  By the time Who Am I? was released in 2007, the number of found children was 88. A new version, released in 2014, provides updates to the story, including the discovery of "Grandchild 114" Guido, the grandson of Estela Carlotto. Carlotto was one of the founders and president of the Grandmothers del Plaza de Mayo and had been searching for her grandson for almost forty years. Upon its release in 2007, Who Am I? won the Coral Award at the International Festival of New Latin American Cinema; the Telesur Award for Best Documentary on Latin America; Best Documentary at the Toronto Film Festival; Audience Popularity Award at the Cinesul Film Festival in Rio de Janerio; and the Elizabeth Cady Stanton Award at the High Falls Film Festival in Rochester, NY.
  - Who Am I: The Found Children of Argentina, 2007; cuid18495; 590460 (Box 73, Dvd 11)
    This is a full-length version of the film Who Am I: The Found Children of Argentina.
  - Who Am I: The Found Children of Argentina "Work in Progress", 2007; cuid18496; 590493 (Box 73, Dvd 12)
  - "3 Mothers Desaparecidos", circa 2007; cuid18497; 479639 (Box 56, Cassette ref1296)
    This recording may be from Who Am I: The Found Children of Argentina, but it could also be from Missing Children.
  - "Argentina Dr. Liwsky, visuals, neon signs", circa 2007; cuid18498; 479632 (Box 56, Cassette ref1290)
  - "Argentina's Found Children", circa 2007; cuid18499; 467398 (Box 29, Cassette ref655)
  - "Argentina's Found Children", circa 2007; cuid18500; 467392 (Box 29, Cassette ref661)
  - "Argentina's Found Children", circa 2007; cuid18501; 467391 (Box 29, Cassette ref662)
  - "Argentina's Found Children", circa 2007; cuid18502; 467390 (Box 30, Cassette ref663)
  - "Argentina's Found Children", circa 2007; cuid18503; 467387 (Box 30, Cassette ref666)
  - "Argentina's Found Children", circa 2007; cuid18504; 467385 (Box 30, Cassette ref668)
  - "Argentina's Found Children", circa 2007; cuid18505; 467382 (Box 30, Cassette ref671)
  - "Argentina's Found Children Sacha (DV2)", circa 2007; cuid18506; 479629 (Box 56, Cassette ref1287)
  - "Argentina's Found Children- Estela escuela Tatiana", circa 2007; cuid18507; 467397 (Box 29, Cassette ref656)
  - "Argentina's Found Children (Rossetti)", circa 2007; cuid18508; 467386 (Box 30, Cassette ref667)
  - Buenos Aires, view of people in Plaza de Mayo, "tal vez el amor", 2005 August 22; cuid18509; 479630 (Box 56, Cassette ref1288)
  - "Camps Plaza Mayo", undated; cuid18510; 467389 (Box 30, Cassette ref664)
  - "Found Children", circa 2007; cuid18511; 467393 (Box 29, Cassette ref660)
  - "Gatica ICAIC", undated; cuid18512; 479637 (Box 56, Cassette ref1294)
  - "Home of the grandmothers," "Sacha and Carla," Estela Carlotto," and "Photos of children", circa 2007; cuid18513; 479636 (Box 56, Cassette ref1293)
  - "Buenos Aires street, grandmothers, wheelchair, Estela", circa 2007; cuid18514; 479638 (Box 56, Cassette ref1295)
  - On Street Interviews and visuals Florida, circa 2007; cuid18515; 479633 (Box 56, Cassette ref1291)
  - Press and Promotion, 2005, 2014; cuid18516; 592989 (Box 72, Folder 26)
  - "Programa TV con las abuelas Rosa y Estela", undated; cuid18517; 467388 (Box 30, Cassette ref665)
  - "Universidad" (Possibly Buenos Aires University), undated; cuid18518; 479631 (Box 56, Cassette ref1289)
- Series XXVIII: Who's Running the Show, 1987; 479620
  For four days, during Easter Week in 1987, the Argentine people demonstrated in the streets to prevent a military coup that threatened to overturn the elected government. The title of the documentary is taken from a popular chant of the protesters, which asked, "Who's running the show - the military or the people?"
  The 28-minute documentary Who's Running the Show? (Quien Dinge la Batuta) is narrated by Ernesto Bravo, and follows a news reporting style with on-the-street interviews by Estela Bravo to capture the opinions of the protesters and people in the area. The film also shows footage of crowds during the protests, and reactions of elected officials.
  - Who's Running the Show? (Quien Dirige la Batuta), 1987; cuid18519; 468048 (Box 89, Cassette ref5, Box 75, Dvd ref5)
    This is a full-length version of the film Who's Running the Show? (Quien Dinge la Batuta). This film is in Spanish.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:28:00.
  - Who's Running the Show? (Quien Dirige la Batuta), circa 1995; cuid18520; 479622 (Box 55, Cassette ref1280, Box 98, Dvd ref1280)
    This video features a complete version of the documentary Who's Running the Show (Quien Dirige la Batuta).
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:28:26.
  - "Running the Show- Pepe in Chile", circa 1987; cuid18521; 467372 (Box 31, Cassette ref681)
- Series XXIX: Independent and Unidentified Footage, 1980-2014; 479079
  The series contains an assortment of recordings. Some of the videos contain footage that was shot independently, and not for a specific film. Examples of these recordings include clips from Brazil, from Mexico, and an interview concerning the Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia (FARC). This series also contains several clips relating to Nelson Mandela for which the specific film cannot be determined. Other footage that cannot be associated with a specific film due to lack of contextual information is also included in this series. An example is an interview Bravo conducted with three individuals in New York. The original box annotations suggest that these individuals are Dominicans but there is no indication of the specific film. The conversation with these individuals continues on more than one cassette. It is unclear whether this is independent material or may have been created for a specific film.
  - "2nd Anniversary of the War of the Malvinas (No Borrar)", undated; cuid18522; 479681 (Box 59, Cassette ref1338)
  - Rosenberg Memorial Ceremony, undated; cuid401; 479404 (Box 63, Cassette ref1065, Box 96, Dvd ref1065)
    This video features two minutes of a Cuban news report on a memorial ceremony in honor of Julius and Ethel Rosenberg at the Rosenberg Memorial in Havana. The footage features Estela Bravo at the ceremony and includes several short interviews with participants discussing the significance of the memorial. After 2:25 the news report ends and the remainder of the video features lyrics and instrumental music from a karaoke program.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:30:44.
  - "Airport, Alarcon", 1994 August 31; cuid18523; 479399 (Box 47, Cassette ref1060, Box 98, Dvd ref1060)
    This video features stitched together segments, which appear to be early edits for the documentary Mareilitos or The Cuban Excludables. The footage begins with Ricardo Alarcón arriving in Cuba. He delivers a short public speech about illegal immigration to the United States and US policy toward Cuba. The remaining footage focuses on individuals attempting to travel to Florida from Cuba on rafts. Some of the footage repeats, and several portions contain voice over narration. Footage also features a brief interview segment with American diplomat Wayne Smith.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:08:42.
  - "Arrival to Cuba", 1994; cuid18524; 479501 (Box 50, Cassette ref1159)
    This recording may be associated with either the Cuban Excludables or Miami-Havana.
  - "Balsero Iglesia Raul Suarez", undated; cuid18525; 467620 (Box 92, Cassette ref433, Box 81, Dvd ref433)
    Reverend Raul Suarez is the founder and director of the Martin Luther King, Jr. Center in Havana. He was pastor of the Cuban Ebenezer Baptist Church from 1971-2005, and served for a time as president of the Council of Churches.
  - "Balsero Museum #49", undated; cuid18526; 479407 (Box 63, Cassette ref1068)
  - "Balseros (rafters) US Coast Guard ABC News", 1991 November 7; cuid18527; 479509 (Box 50, Cassette ref1167)
  - "Bloque II", undated; cuid18528; 479511 (Box 50, Cassette ref1169)
  - "Brazil", undated; cuid18529; 467666 (Box 92, Cassette ref387, Box 80, Dvd ref387)
  - "Brazil Football", undated; cuid18530; 479705 (Box 59, Cassette ref1358)
  - Bump: Widow of Luciano Nieves; Felipe Rivero; Bryan O. Walsh; and Various Films, undated; cuid402; 479664 (Box 66, Cassette ref1321, Box 98, Dvd ref1321)
    Filipe Rivero was a Cuban exile who participated involved in the Bay of Pigs invasion and anti-Castro political activism in Miami.
    This video features three interviews and a series of video clips recorded from television programs. The first interview features the widow of Cuban pacifist Luciano Nieves. She discusses her husband's assassination, and describes him as a pioneer for calling for improved relations between the US and Cuba in the 1970s. The second interview features anti-Castro political activist Felipe Rivero. Rivero discusses his involvement in the Bay of Pigs invasion and addresses criticism about members of his movement who have been charged with or convicted of terrorism. He specifically discusses members of his organization who were convicted for the assassination of Chilean diplomat Orlando Letelier. The third interview features Miami priest Father Bryan Walsh. Walsh discusses his role in sponsoring Cuban children traveling to the US without their parents between 1960 and 1962, and the US government's role in supporting that work. The final 30 minutes to the tape feature assorted clips recorded from television. Video and audio quality is very poor and the bulk of the content on the second half of this tape is difficult to view.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 01:02:31.
  - "Carnavales de Estela Bravo", undated; cuid18531; 479742 (Box 49, Cassette ref1395)
  - "Cuba Central Puerto Artemisa", undated; cuid18532; 467463 (Box 87, Cassette ref590, Box 82, Dvd ref590)
  - Documentary List and Trailer, 2014; TW_TAM_616_ER_12
  - Estela and Ernesto Bravo Interview, undated; TW_TAM_616_ER_13
  - Fajardo, Panchita: footage; Create the Future film, undated; cuid18537; 467227 (Box 94, Cassette ref826, Box 83, Dvd ref826)
    Dr. Francisca Rivera Arocha, also known as Panchita Fajardo, was one of the early female physicians in Cuba. Her son, Major Manuel 'Piti' Fajardo Rivera, was also a physician. He was killed during the Revolution; her daughter-in-law was a professor of medicine who worked with Ernesto Bravo.
    The first approximately 12 minutes involve Panchita Fajardo. The footage features discussions between Estela Bravo and Fajardo, as well as moments with Raul and Fidel Castro, and Carlos Rafael Rodriguez.
    The next part begins with Fidel Castro speaking about energy. The clip is followed by a short film produced by the Atomic Energy Commission of Cuba titled Create the Future, which runs from 00:13:45 - 00:26:00. The film is in Spanish.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:27:00.
  - Footage: Rally Against United States Intervention in El Salvador, circa 1990; cuid798; 467223 (Box 43, Cassette ref830, Box 95, Dvd ref830)
    This video features footage of a rally in the United States protesting the US Government's intervention in El Salvador. The footage begins with a brief interview of a couple from Argentina, who discuss their imprisonment by the Argentinian government for political activism and discuss Argentina's support of the military junta in El Salvador. The footage features other interviews with members of the crowd about their reasons for participating in the rally. Speakers at the rally can be heard off camera, but are not filmed. This footage does not appear to be filmed by Estela Bravo.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:14:01
  - House on Aguila Street: Interview with Dina, Mercedes, and Ramon, 1992 March 1; cuid18538; 479729 (Box 60, Cassette ref1382, Box 98, Dvd ref1382)
    This video features an interview with three Cuban youths and their neighbor. The neighbor begins by explaining that the children were abandoned by their mother in 1980, when she left Cuba for the United States in the Mariel Boatlift. The eldest daughter explains that she was 11 years old at the time, and she and her siblings did not know how to care for themselves. They explains that they were able to survive with financial support from the government, and assistance from their neighbor who tried to help them as much as she could. At the time the interview was recorded in 1991, the family had not been able to locate their mother, and they did not know if she was still living.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:26:49.
  - Interview on anti-Castro Terrorism, undated; cuid18539; 467465 (Box 87, Cassette ref588, Box 82, Dvd ref588)
    This video begins with stills of a wedding, and the remainder is footage is a young man speaking in Spanish. He talks about attacks and assassinations carried out by far-right-wing, anti-Castro terrorist groups, mentioning a bombing of the Cuban Mission to the UN carried out by a New Jersey-based group Omega 7. He also speaks about the larger context of these groups and discusses the assassinations of Orlando Letelier, Carlos Muniz, and Eulalio Negrin. He describes the origin of these organizations and suggests that many of their actions are motivated by anti-Castro propaganda from the United States.
  - Interview with Dominicans, End of Interview ("Car, Children, Nothing Special" ) B roll, undated; cuid18541; 477190 (Box 70, Cassette ref931, Box 85, Dvd ref931)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:03:13.
  - Interview re: FARC, undated; cuid18542; 467459 (Box 87, Cassette ref594, Box 82, Dvd ref594)
    This is an interview (in Spanish) with Raul Herrera or Viera, a FARC member, who discusses the history of the organization and its goals, as well as its view of US imperialism and US policies in Latin America after the Cuban Revolution. He talks about guerilla movements and the use of violence, and about a war for peace and social and economic reform. He also speaks about Camilo Torres as a hero in Colombia.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:23:00.
  - Interviews on the Streets of Havana (On the corner of H and 21st streets), undated; cuid18543; 479692 (Box 60, Cassette ref1349, Box 98, Dvd ref1349)
    This video features on-the-street interviews with people in Havana discussing families divided between the United States and Cuba. A small portion of the interviewees discuss their family members who are in the United States and the difficulty of reconnecting them. They discuss the difficulty of obtaining visas to see their family in the US, and the pain of family separation. The majority of the people featured in the video, however, state that they do not have family abroad and talk generally about their pride as Cubans and their desire to stay in their country. Others discuss their opposition to the US blockade and US policy toward Cuba.